

Olivier Eeckhoutte

Freelance Solution Architect/ Technical Lead/ Senior Backend developer/ DevOps

15+ years of professional experience Full Remote only

PROFILE

I feel lucky to work in a field I am very passionated about and evolves quickly.

Passionated about new technologies and very curious, I like to design and develop useful solutions and solve complex problems.

I enjoy learning new things all the time, be more and more proficient, discover raw gems and share my new discoveries with others.

I spent 3 years in the USA.

EDUCATION

Engineer of "Ecole Centrale de Lille", Graduated in 2011 Top Engineering School

Entrepreneurship and Management Specialities

Member of Iteem program: Second diploma delivered by top Business school called Skema Business School

(Verification link: https://www.centraliens-lille.org/fr/addressbook/fullsearch/index)

CONTACT INFORMATIONS

+33 6 95 24 43 62

olivier.eeckhoutte@gmail.com Location: Morbihan, France

Professional Blog: https://leandeep.com (Articles

about my technical skills)

Linkedin: https://bit.ly/oeeckhout (Detailed profile)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Backend Developer, Breitling, Switzerland

Dec 2023 - Today

- Building from the ground up Breitling's new e-commerce platform leveraging Saleor E-commerce Headless solution
- Development of event driven micro services in Python & GraphQL hosted in AWS on Kubernetes
- Pushing best practices (development, devops, tooling, practices) and proven working solutions from past experiences in an international team

Lead DevOps, TAG Heuer, Switzerland

Nov 2019 - Dev 2023 (4+ years)

- Developments of the cloud & python based middleware (custom Enterprise Service Bus) and API between the ecommerce website, Retail systems and lot's of internal backends systems
 —> More on this successful innovative platform here https://bit.ly/3gs0EHY and here https://bit.ly/3C0hX9W
- Developments of the custom made CIAM (Customer IAM) built on top of Keyclaok using python + LDAP migration + Keycloak plugin development
- Contributed to a new Ecom headless platform and other Web based platforms
- Managed different Azure/ Kubernetes cluster builds and migrations
- Setup all kind of different DevOps automations (Terraform, CI/ CD, Automated Tests, Monitoring...)
- Creation of an enterprise cross-channels Business Activity
 Monitoring (BAM) using a data stack (i.e. pandas, streamlit...)
- Tons of problems solved

KEY SKILLS

Architecture

Clean Architecture, CQRS, Serverless,
Micro Services, API Gateway, Service
Mesh, SOA, Message Oriented
Architecture with topics and queues
(Kafka, Azure Service Bus, RabbitMQ...)
SQL (MySQL, Postgres), NoSQL
(MongoDB, Redis, CouchBase,
ElasticSearch, Influx, DynamoDB...)
SSO (keycloak), Oauth2, OIDC, Vault,
UML, IoT, Enterprise Workflows
(Camunda), REST, GraphQL

Data Science

Python, BigQuery, Machine Learning (scikit-learn, Pandas, TensorFlow/ Keras, Neural networks, FastAl, PyTorch), RPA, Scaping, Chatbots, AWS Al tools, Kubeflow, Prefect, Airflow

DevOps/ Cloud

Azure, Amazon Web Services, GCP,
Docker, Monitoring, Tests Automation,
Linux (RedHat 7, CentOS, Debian),
Continuous Delivery, Software Factory
(Github, AWS CodePipeline, Gitlab,
CircleCl, Azure Devops, Bitbucket...),
Nginx, Kubernetes + custom dev
operators, OpenShift (v3.6 to v4), Hub &
Spoke Architecture, Terraform, 12
Factors

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Backend Developer (in parallel of my main job at TAG Heuer)

Sept 2023 - Jan 2023 (customer: DLG Group, Switzerland)

 Marketing app (full backend realised from A to Z in Python and hosted in Google Cloud. I don't communicate on the details until it is officially launched)

Web3 trader/ Arbitrager (in parallel of my main job at TAG Heuer & then at Breitling)

Jul 2020 - Today (customer: myself)

- Who better than yourself can take care of your finances?
- As I don't believe banks or other financial institutions will really take care of my money I simply automate everything to make my personal portfolio grow by trading on crypto exchanges (CeFI and DeFi) and by building decision making bots

Co-Technical Leader, Engie Trading Center, Brussels

Apr 2019 - Nov 19 (6 months)

- Create reusable and transversal tools for the developer teams
 (Data access management, automated end to end tests tools)
- Co-Technical Lead in an international team made of developers, data engineers & data analysts
- Migration OVH to AWS

DevOps, Adeo group, France

Feb 2018 - Apr 2019 (1+ year)

- Setup and Manage large Platform As A Service (> 300 servers)
- Cloud Hybrid (On-Premise Google Cloud Platform)
- DevOps, Cloud Native Architecture
- Trainings creation and animation (Kubernetes, CI/CD Tools, Openshift, Continuous Delivery)
- Agile Methodology training and technical evangelisation
- SRE (Site Reliability Engineering): development, automation, monitoring (Python, Ansible, Terraform, Prometheus...)

KEY SKILLS

Blockchain

Nodes hosting, DeFi protocols, Advanced backend Web3 development, Solidity, Rust, Security, Hardhat, IPFS

Web/ Mobile/ Backend dev

Javascript (Svelte, AngularJS, Angular 2+, Ionic, Backbone...), SPA,
Responsive Web Design, NodeJS,
Webpack, HTML5 (WebRTC,
WebSockets, Service Workers...),
Cordova, iOS, Android, PHP, Java,
TypeScript, Vue, Progressive Web Apps,
TDD, BDD, DDD, Git, Python

Project management/ Methods

Scrum, Kanban, Holacracy, Software
Craftsmanship, Lean Management, Lean
Startup, Design Thinking

Ecommerce

Salesforce.com, Salesforce Commerce Cloud, Saleor, Adyen, Paazl, SAP oData, Cegid, Forter, Riskified, Cegid, Akeneo, Bynder, GlobalE, Yext and other ecommerce related SAAS (Mailchimp, Twilio...)

Embedded dev/ Edge Computing

ESP32, Rust, Jetson, k3s, balena, micropython, sensors

Finance/ Administration

Web3 trading, Administration: I manage my own company

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Technical Leader (& Data Champion), SwissLife

Mar 2015 - Feb 2018 (3 years)

- Technical Lead "Digital Solutions" (Design and development of the main customer portal)
- Transversal communities (Developers & DevOps) animator
- Dissemination of Agile & Software Craftsmanship + Continuous
 Delivery best practices
- Data Champion (Big Data /Machine Learning / Cloud migration contributor)
- Applicative Architecture Design
- Many innovation Studies and Proof Of Concept done
- Cognitive technologies referent

Entrepreneurship (in parallel of my work at SwissLife)

Apr 2016 - Feb 2018

- Design and development of IoT object to open gates with face recognition
 - Automatic Tensorflow Models trainings engine manageable with Web/ Mobile interface
 - Deep Learning on Mobile devices and OTA updates
- Trainer in Project Management with Scrum, Lean Startup and Holacracy (School: ISCOM)
- Innovation Workshop Organiser (School: ISCOM)
- Startup Advisor (Technology stack): (Company: LaFinbox)
- AngularJS, NodeJS in Test Driven Development trainer

CTO, Geophyle, France (startup of 15 people)

Mar 2014 - Mar 2015 (1 year)

- Team Management (7 developers)
- Architecture, Design and development of the solutions
- Projet Management (Budget / Planning / Ressources)
- Recruiting

LANGUAGES

French English

TRAININGS & CERTIFICATIONS

No recent training but I continue to learn continuously. It's a passion

- 2021 Learn how to integrate Django with Vue.js, MOOC
- 2021 Ethereum and Solidity Developer Bootcamp, MOOC
- 2020 The Complete 2020 Ethereum and Solidity Developer

Bootcamp, MOOC, Packtpub

- 2020 Learn to trade indexes, MOOC
- 2020 Forex trading with Ichimoku, MOOC
- 2019 Typescript fundamentals, MOOC
- 2019 Learning Blockchain Dev with EOS and C++, MOOC
- 2018 Google Cloud Platform introduction, Google, Lille
- 2017 Scalable Microservices with Kubernetes, Google, Lille
- 2017 Running Container Clusters with Kubernetes, MOOC
- 2017 Certif. Lean Management Introduction, Advanced Path
- 2017 Data Science, Advanced level, OCTO, Paris
- 2016 Introduction to statistics with R, MOOC
- 2016 Data Science foundations, OCTO, Paris
- 2016 Apache Spark essentials, MOOC
- 2016 Udacity, Georgia Tech, Kaggle, NanoDegree

Program: 420h of online training about Machine Learning

- 2016 Certif. AWS Solutions Architect Associate
- 2016 Machine Learning, Stanford, Course Certificate, MOOC
- 2016 Certif, Intermediate Python For Data Science,

Datacamp

- 2016 Amazon Web Services for Data Science, MOOC
- 2016 Mastering Software Development, Arolla, Paris
- 2016 Holacracy, IGI Partners, Training + 4 month mentoring
- 2016 Docker and Container Technologies, MOOC
- 2013 CEH v7 Training and Certification, Sysdream, Paris
- 2012 Certif, Energy Manager Professional, Schneider, Boston

RECOMMANDATIONS ON DEMAND

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Application Architect, Schneider-Electric France

Mar 2013 - Mar 2014 (1 year)

- Startup Creation Intrapreneurship project
- Facility Management Cross-Platforms Application (https://youtu.be/gl9t-XTco18)
- Architecture & Development lead (AWS, Web, Mobile, NoSQL)

Team/ Technical Leader, Schneider-Electric USA

Jul 2009 - Mar 2013 (4.5 years)

- Mobile Cross-Platforms architectures design & development
- Technical advisor in the strategy & Innovation department
- Mobile development Companies buyout auditor

OTHER EXPERIENCES

Internships

- Developer, Arc International (2 months internship 2008)
- Salesman, Leroy Merlin plumbing shelf (3 months internship 2007)

Others

- At home computers repair (from 2005 to 2008)
- Big Data & Machine Learnin Meetup Organizer, Lille, 2018
- Public speaking (i.e: Nutigo, Big Data & Machine Learning,
 YO'Meet, during lot's Hackathons...)

HOBBIES

-	Creative	-	Security	-	Hacking
	workshops	-	Woodworking	-	Politics
-	Beerology	-	Windsurfing	-	3D Printing
-	Travels	-	Walking in Nature	-	Tech or Financia
-	Wing foil	-	Standup Paddle		podcasts while
-	Sailing	-	Biking		running
-	Investing	-	Coding	-	Judo (black belt)